Finding Aid for Clark J. Charnetski papers.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Clark J. Charnetski papers
1955-1971
1966-1970
Charnetski, Clark J.
2014075 Aa 2
Papers of Clark J. Charnetski (1942- ), a physicist who specialized in holographic research and development at Conductron Corporation in Ann Arbor, Mich., where he was the Associate Research Physicist and Chief Holographer. This collection contains materials relating to the administrative background of Conductron Corporation, materials relating to holography in Michigan collected by Charnetski, papers and presentations given by Charnetski and Conductron Corporation, notes, drawings, information relating to patents of Charnetski and others at Conductron, as well as detailed papers regarding the projects that Charnetski conducted while at Conductron.
3.1 linear feet in 4 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection was donated by Clark J. Charnetski (donor no. 11060 ) in February 2014.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open to research.
Clark J. Charnetski was born in 1942 in Menominee, Mich. to Victor and Theresa Charnetski. He received his Bachelor of Science degree in Physics from the University of Michigan in 1964. One year later, he married Mary Ann Lund. After his graduation from the University of Michigan, Charnetski taught high school physics and physical science in Walled Lake, Mich. for two years.
In 1966, Charnetski joined the Optics Research department of Conductron Corporation in Ann Arbor, Mich. Conductron Corporation was a 1960's electronics and radar research firm which was founded by Keeve (Kip) Siegel, a former Physics professor at the University of Michigan, with the goal of commercializing and furthering the work of the University of Michigan's Radiation Laboratory during the developmental years of holography. Conductron was key to early holographic research and innovation and many of the methods and techniques used today, including full-color holography, can trace their roots back to Conductron.
During his time at Conductron, Charnetski conducted extensive research in holography. Charnetski was the Associate Research Physicist and Chief Holographer in the Electro-Optical Department at Conductron and worked mainly in commercial holographic displays. He produced the master hologram and devised the means to print 500,000 holograms for binding into World Book's 1967 Science Year annual supplement, which at the time was the largest order for holograms ever made. In 1968, Charnetski made the four 18 by 24 inch holograms used for the General Motors (GM) Fisher Body display in GM's new office building in New York City, which were the largest size holograms of their time.
The Clark J. Charnetski papers contain materials relating to the administrative background of Conductron Corporation, materials relating to holography in Michigan collected by Charnetski, papers and presentations given by Charnetski and Conductron Corporation, notes, drawings, information relating to patents of Charnetski and others at Conductron, as well as detailed papers regarding the projects that Charnetski conducted while at Conductron. This collection is of value to those interested in the history of holography, especially as it relates to the state of Michigan. The collection is divided into four series: the Administrative series, the Scientific Works series (divided into three subseries: Collected Materials, Papers and Presentations, and Patents and Inventions), the Projects series, and the Mechanical Drawings series.
Subjects:
Charnetski, Clark J.; Conductron Corporation--Michigan--Ann Arbor.MichiganAnn Arbor.; Holography--Michigan.; Holography industry--Michigan.; Research and development projects--Holography.
Genre Terms:
Black-and-white negatives.; Drafting.; Holography.; Photographs.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series (0.8 linear feet, 1965-1971) contains materials relating to Conductron Corporation. This includes business correspondence, articles written about Conductron Corporation, Charnetski's desk calendar with daily notes, annual and monthly reports, company newsletters, holography marketing materials, film samples, staff information, and products and equipment used by Conductron Corporation (including photographs). Notable in this series is information regarding the holograms used in World Book's 1967 Science Year.
  - Business correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 1)
  - Charnetski's desk calendar
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
  - Conductron annual report holograms, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Conductron articles, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Conductron binder materials, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Conductron management, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Conductron newsletters-Antenna, 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with AGFA-GEVAERT, 1966-1970 (Box 1)
  - Film inventories, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Holography marketing materials, 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - Kalvar Corporation materials, 1965-1970 (Box 1)
  - Kingsport Press and Field Enterprises World Book Science Year supplement, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Large lens calibration cards, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Laser safety, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Library information, 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous work orders, 1966-1970 (Box 1)
  - Monthly reports, 1968 (Box 1)
  - National Advertising Company (3M) presentation, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Optics department staff, 1965-1971 (Box 1)
  - Photograph-Conductron Missouri simulator, undated (Box 1)
  - Procedure governing relocation of Ann Arbor Conductron personnel to St. Charles, Missouri, undated (Box 1)
  - Products used by Conductron, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Pulsed hologram viewer, 1968; 2 photographs (Box 1)
  - Reflection hologram samples, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Staff directories, 1966-1970 (Box 1)
  - Three B Optical Company production bulletin, undated (Box 1)
  - Time cards
    - 1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan photographs of equipment, 1968; 6 photographs (Box 1)
  - Visitors to Conductron, 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - Weekly work summaries
    - Clark Charnetski, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - David Wender, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
- Scientific works
  The Scientific works series (0.8 linear feet, 1955-1970) is a collection of materials related to the scientific study of holography. The series has been divided into three subseries: Collected materials, Papers and presentations, and Patents and inventions.
  - Collected materials
    The Collected materials subseries (0.2 linear feet, 1955-1970) contains materials relating to Emmett Leith, Juris Upatnieks, and George Stroke and their work with holography at the University of Michigan. In addition, materials relating to other companies and physicists throughout Michigan and their holographic innovations are included in this series.
    - Emmett Leith materials, 1963-1970 (Box 1)
    - George Stroke materials, 1955-1968 (Box 1)
    - Holography and Michigan, 1966-1970 (Box 1)
    - Juris Upatnieks materials, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Papers and presentations
    The Papers and presentations subseries (0.4 linear feet, 1966-1970) contains all of the publications written by Charnetski in addition to marked up drafts and notes. Presentations given by Charnetski to different groups (with some photographs of presentations) and papers and presentations given by others at Conductron are also included in this series.
    - American Institute of Chemical Engineers presentation, 1970 (Box 1)
    - ASTME Vectors, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Charnetski-Miscellaneous notes with, 1968-1969; undated (Box 1)
    - Color screen holograms, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Conductron papers, 1966-1970 (Box 2)
    - Correcting Perspective Distortion, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Holography--Modern Magic, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Holography, New Field of Photography, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Holography Today, 1968 (Box 2)
    - The Impact of Holography on the Consumer, 1970 (Box 2)
    - McDonnell Aircraft Company seminar, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Optical Society of America Annual meetings, 1967-1969 (Box 2)
    - Optical Society of America Fall meeting, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Optical Society of America Spring meetings, 1968-1970 (Box 2)
    - Photographs of Optical Society of America presentation, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Reprint requests-Holography Today, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Patents and inventions
    Patents and inventions subseries (0.2 linear feet, 1966-1970) relates to materials regarding patents and inventions of Clark Charnetski, as well as those of others at Conductron Corporation. Included in this series are invention disclosures, contracts, and notes regarding inventions, as well as a list of Conductron personnel invention disclosures.
    - Contact prints of holograms, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Holographic comparator, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Holographic template, 1969 (Box 2)
    - List of Conductron invention disclosures, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Patent information on focused image reflection holograms, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Photographic printing of holograms, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Real image reflection hologram, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Transmission-reflection hologram, 1968 (Box 2)
- Projects
  The Projects series (1 linear foot, 1967-1970) holds materials relating to the various holographic projects that Charnetski worked on during his time at Conductron Corporation. This includes notes taken by Charnetski regarding projects, project sketches drawn by Charnetski, photographs corresponding to projects, and project orders and other processing documents.
  - Acoustic holographic resolution (photographs and negatives), undated (Box 2)
  - Beam splitters, undated (Box 2)
  - Coherence length, undated (Box 2)
  - Color holograms, undated (Box 2)
  - Distortion correction, 1968; 6 photographs (Box 2)
  - Educational holograms, undated (Box 2)
  - Ellipses on plates-large collimators, undated (Box 2)
  - Ellipsoidal mirror (large) Ray Trace study, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Ford display prints, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - F-15 heads up display, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Gunsight Recording Camera System, 1965 (Box 2)
  - High production holograms, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Hologram viewer, undated (Box 2)
  - Holographic NDT of turbine blades, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Holographic template, undated; 2 photographs (Box 2)
  - Holographic vacuum system schematics, undated (Box 2)
  - Houdaille Hydraulics hologram proposal, 1970 (Box 2)
  - IR&D holography research and development, 1968 (Box 2)
  - IR&D proposals, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Large collimators, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Large lens, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Mass production of reflection film holograms, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Mix master hologram, undated (Box 2)
  - Moon spatial filtering, undated; 4 photographs (Box 2)
  - National Cash Register Company hologram inquiry, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Project 748 process and routing sheets, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Project 971: Pen aids holograms, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 1017 General Motors Fisher Body display, 1968 (Box 3)
    (2 folders)
  - Project 1024 Hoffmann-La Roche stomach wall, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Project 1073 McDonnell-Douglas Company reflection holograms, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Project 1090 Hoffmann-La Roche spastic colon holograms, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Project 1146 Bruce Nauman portrait (with photographs), 1968 (Box 3)
  - Project 1147 Professor Richard Wilt holograms, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Project 1160 General Motors flying saucer holograms, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 1198 Hoffman-La Roche eye reach III holograms, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 1217 Mead Packaging holograms, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 1223 Smithsonian Institution reflection holograms, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Project 1251 Oceanography Development Corporation holograms, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Project 1252 Toro Lawn Mower hologram, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Project 1968-070: Hologram resolution study (Box 3)
  - Project 1969-130: IR&D Hologram applications, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Project 3412 Marketing masters for reflection hologram samples, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 3903 Head-up display holograms, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 4124 Holographic apparatus purchases, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Project 5012 CATV holograms, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Project 5309 Pulsed laser holography, undated (Box 3)
  - Project 5314 Transmission film holograms, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Project 6005 F-4 Image, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 7176 Reflection holograms for inventory, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Project 7181 Focused image reflection holograms, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 7182 Focused image reflection hologram of F-111, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 7187 Clock, magnifier, and molecule holograms, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 7190 Focused image reflection holograms of F-4 airplane, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 7196 Clock-magnifier holograms, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Project 7197 Hologram of skier, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Pulsed laser particle sizing interferometry, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Ray Trace-Large plane-convex lenses, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Reflection film holograms for point-of-purchase store displays, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Small focused image holograms, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Society of Automotive Engineers exhibit, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Three Dimensional Image Systems and Optical data Processing Systems Research and development, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Wavelength compensation for holograms, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Wind Tunnel Holographic Feasibility study, 1967 (Box 3)
  - 360 degree hologram, 1968 (Box 3)
- Mechanical drawings
  The Mechanical drawings series (0.5 linear feet, 1966-1969) is a collection of various mechanical drawings relating to holography.
  - Beamsplitter mounts, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Holographic adjustable mirror mount, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Holographic movie projector, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Holographic plate holder 4 by 5 inch, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Holographic plate holder assembly 8 by 10 inch, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Mirror base, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Mirror mount, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Modified pinhole assembly, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Octopus lamphouse, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Pinhole assemblies, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Pulsed laser hologram viewer, 1968 (Box 4)
Related Collections
The Bentley Historical Library holds the following related manuscript collections:
Emmett N. Leith papers, 1936 and 1954-2005. Finding aid available online
Keeve Milton Siegel papers, 1953-1983. Finding aid available online
Juris Upatnieks papers, 1963-1994. Finding aid available online